Ryan Swift

Denver, CO · 443-632-7020 · swift.ryan.w@gmail.com

Senior Full Stack Developer and Software Engineer. Experience leading the design, development, testing, and deployment of multiple customer facing full stack applications. Strong problem solving engineer proven to learn new skills as needed to complete tasks promptly. Interested in software consulting, full stack development, and leading other engineers. Prefer to design and build meaningful applications with smaller teams over maintaining legacy applications.

Technical Experience

Languages Typescript, JavaScript, Go, Python, Java, SQL, HTML/CSS

Software and Applications AWS Services, AWS CDK, Docker, React, ORMs, GraphQL, Node.js, Next.js,

Express.js, Auth0, Sendgrid, Spring, AMQP, Kafka, Snowflake, Kubernetes

Databases PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Aurora, DocumentDB

Tools Github, Github Actions, AWS CodeBuild, NPM, Gitlab CI

Other Agile and Kanban, Continuous Integration and Continuous Deployment (CI/CD),

Git, Infrastructure as Code (IaC), Linux, MacOS

Work Experience

SPECIFX, Denver, Colorado

Senior Software Engineer | March 2023 - Present

- Hired as the company's first full stack web developer, designer, and engineer to bring a prototype application that simplifies HVAC asset data to enterprise customers
- Designed and built the web application programming interface (API) and database schema from scratch while implementing a multitenant architecture for organization and team management to replace the prototype backend including selecting the tech stack
- Built all of the company's AWS environments using AWS CDK for IaC to handle Fargate service connections, service auto scaling, web application routing using Route 53, security privileges, database connections, and more
- Introduced CI pipelines using Github Actions and AWS CodeBuild to build the entire application stack on specific repository branch actions
- Advocated and created an internal administrator web application for managing customer account creation, customer information, customer use, and application performance metrics
- Integrated authentication and authorization permission handling in the web applications and APIs using Auth0
- Enhance web application interface to introduce navigation, organization structures, and visual clarity by designing solutions with our Chief Product Officer based on customer feedback
- Lead the Agile methodology integration at the company; including leading backlog creation and grooming, daily status, sprint planning, and retrospectives
- Lead by example to create single source of truth documentation at the company and developer documentation
- Rebuilt the company's corporate website including adding an automated contact form email that is delivered to the company's point of contact for sales
- Designing and developing a machine-to-machine focused API to integrate customer's systems with the company's services
- Manage all web application software deployments for new feature releases

CHARGENET STATIONS, Denver, Colorado

Senior Software Engineer | September 2022 – January 2023

- Created the complete AWS infrastructure for a new internal project to be used by the software team, operations team, financiers, and owners of the charging sites
- Developer for backend AWS microservices that communicate with third party electric vehicle (EV) chargers over open charge point protocol (OCPP)
- Contributor for a React Native application that allows customers to charge their vehicles by querying our backend services using GraphQL
- Lead project innovation by participating in both high level architectural discussions and low level technical discussions and creating proposals for the software team leads after researching various full stack application solutions
- Interviewed software engineering interns and planned to lead multiple interns in the summer of 2023
- Contributed to the future of the company by interviewing full-time software engineering candidates
- Produced an automated email reporting service for leadership using Apache Airflow deployed on AWS after setting up a Snowflake data warehouse for querying

TRUSTED SPACE INC, Denver, Colorado

Software Engineer | April 2021 - September 2022

- Developer for a custom and dynamic frontend web application for object catalogs and object threat analysis, assessment, and mitigation
- Contributed to the Trusted Space Software Factory to build software with a DevSecOps and Agile approach
- Developed full stack microservices, from API to persistence, and CI/CD pipelines for an object catalog and behavior analysis application
- Developed metric and analysis offline full stack web applications for the modeling and simulation group in the DARPA Blackjack program to help determine mission performance
- Performed roles as both the Scrum Master and lead developer on a scrum team participating in sprint planning, retrospective, and close out activities
- Acted as a software engineering subject matter expert to help the company grow as a small business including R&D efforts, recruiting, proposal writing, and proposal reviewing

APEX SYSTEMS, Littleton, Colorado

Software Engineer | November 2020 - April, 2021

- Contractor on a Lockheed Martin Space Program
- Developer for mission critical mission control application

RIDGELINE INTERNATIONAL INC, Tysons, Virginia

Full Stack Software Engineer | November 2019 - November 2020

- Developed, maintained, and deployed a full stack web application for persona management to access virtual machines and mobile devices to multiple development and production environments
- Architected and developed a custom web portal to grant users access to online training material given a short time-frame due to the global pandemic
- Worked with multiple open source projects to provide access to many devices through a web browser

L3 HARRIS APPLIED DEFENSE SOLUTIONS, Herndon, Virginia

Software Engineer | February 2017 - October 2019

- Architectural designer and developer for a six month R&D project leading a team of three software engineers and for a 16 month R&D project working with a team of 10 software and aerospace engineers
- Lead developer, integrator, and coordinator for a 12 month contract on DARPA's Hallmark program creating backend processes to perform reachability analysis between various satellites
- Upgraded existing and created RESTful APIs to provide operators with real-time information regarding sensor performance, observational data, and results from algorithmic computations
- Primary DevOps engineer assigned to build Docker containers using continuous integration tools and deploy images to a container orchestration system
- Participated in architectural design discussions, code reviews, and worked in an agile/scrum environment
- Created small prototype level front-end web applications to provide operators a user interface to interact with a large amount of processed data

ACCENTURE FEDERAL SERVICES, Arlington, Virginia

Software Engineering Analyst | August 2016 – February 2017

Education

Johns Hopkins University

June, 2017 - May, 2020 MS Computer Science Engineering for Professionals Program

University of Maryland, College Park

May, 2016
BS Applied Mathematics
Computer Science Minor
Graduate of the Maryland Scholars' Program